Mohammad Merajul Islam Molla Toronto, Canada

Email: meraj.enigma@gmail.com • Mobile: + (1) 647-261-4628 • Skype: mmm2177

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/merajenigma

Github: imeraj

Medium: https://medium.com/@merajulislam

Summary

About 11 years of industry and academic experience work- Have experience working in multiple countries - Canada, ing with diverse technologies ranging from low-level system company strategy & policy making, along with new business development and introducing new technologies to meet dynamic nature of tech industry.

USA, Japan, India, South Korea and with clients from difsoftware to mobile/web applications, project management, ferent countries - Canada, USA, South Korea, Japan, and Australia. Good verbal and written communication skills and comfortable working with colleagues and clients from diverse cultures.

INTERESTS: New Technology R&D, Software Architecture, Mobile Application Development, Web Application Development, Software Quality Assurance, Security, Embedded Systems, Recruitment & Team Building

Experience

Lead Engineer (Web Technology), FlipGive Inc, Toronto, Canada

Dec 2019 - Present

- Working as Lead Engineer of backend integrations team managing two other engineers.
- Worked on transitioning FlipGive's current payment mechanism from Cheque to Bank Transfer by integrating with Hyperwallet (https://www.hyperwallet.com) and Plaid (https://plaid.com).
- Integrated Button (https://www.usebutton.com/) with FlipGive merchants network.
- Designed and built an integration health dashboard to track affiliates network health.

Application Architect (Web Technology), Rakuten Inc, Tokyo, Japan

Jun 2018 - Oct 2019

- Worked as Technical Leader of Event Management Platform (EMP) Web Application (Spring Boot, Angular Js, jBPM, Batch, etc).
- Designed architecture of EMP based on Microservices (Spring Cloud, Spring Cloud Stream, Spring Cloud Contracts) and improved current monolith architecture.
- Interviewed candidates, built teams, and trained members.
- Security Aspects: Microservices authentication mechanism has been handled using OAuth2 and jwt token.

CTO (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

Jan 2017 - Oct 2017

- Supervised Mobile (iOS, Android), Infrastructure, and QA Teams.
- Supervised projects: Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Taxi app (Android) Uber like taxi booking app. Conducted R&D for iOS app.
- Conducted regular trainings, tech talks, and internal tech sessions for high performance team building.
- Was highly involved in recruitment, project estimation, employee evaluation, and company strategy determination.

Senior Architect (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

May 2016 - Dec 2016

- Built and supervised Mobile (iOS, Android) teams from scratch.
- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile projects (iOS, Android).
- Supervised projects: A2MILKBAR departmental store management app (iOS, Android, PHP/Node.js), Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) - E-commerce App (iOS, Android).

Chief Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

Mar 2014 - May 2016

- Worked as Tech Lead of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Manager applications and managed 20+ team members.
- Supervised multiple internal projects for iOS, Android and Tizen platforms Log Analyzer, Emergency Service, TizenFlip, Samsung Guardian App, etc.
- Managed small team of 3 members to contribution to open source project Linaro.

Lead Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD May 2012 - Mar 2014

- Worked as Team Lead of Call and Driver Teams of Feature Phone Mobile Commercialization division and managed around 10+ team members.
- Worked as Tech Lead of Qshare (Quick Share) project on Android platform.

System SW Engineer (MAC OS Graphics Driver Team, NVIDIA, CA, USA

Jan 2008 - Aug 2011

- Worked on various components of Display Drivers and core RM Software (Hotplug Architecture, Display Port, Mobile PCI Express Module (MXM), Interrupt Handling, DVI Port, HDCP Protocol, VBIOS, etc).
- Implemented in C and x86 assembly.

MTS Intern (CPD, VMware ESX Server Team), VMware, CA, USA

May 2007 - Aug 2007

- Developed Kernel Crash Dump tool for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script.

MTS Intern (CPD, VMware ESX Server Team), VMware Inc, CA, USA

May 2006 - Aug 2006

- Developed Filesystem Debugger for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script

Education

Marquette University, MS in Computing

Dec 2007

- CGPA: 4.00/4.00
- Final Project: Implementation of device driver for Broadcom's BCM4713 Ethernet card on Linksys WRT54GL router and integrating it with Xinu Kernel.

BUET, BS in CSE

Nov 2004

- CGPA: 3.92/4.00
- Thesis: Study of Various Popular Network Simulators and Case Studies using NS-2, Commonly Used Open Source Network Research Simulator, to Simulate Wired and Wireless Networks.

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: Ruby • Elixir • Go • Swift • Java • Kotlin • Objective-C • C • C++ • Assembly(x86, MIPS)

Web Frameworks (Backend): Ruby on Rails • Phoenix (Elixir) • Spring Boot • Spring Cloud • Gorilla (golang)

Web Frameworks (Frontend): React • Angular • Phoenix LiveView

Mobile Platforms: iOS • Android

Mobile Architecture Patterns: MVC • MVP • VIP • RxVIP

Mobile Frameworks/Tools: RxSwift • ReSwift • RxJava • Reductor • Alamofire • Retrofit 2 • Glide • Picasso • AlamofireImage • KingFisher • Firebase • Dagger 2 • ARKit • CoreML • Google Analytics

APM Tools: Prometheus • Scout • AppSignal • New Relic

Quality Assurance: Cucumber • Calabash • XCTest • ExUnit • RSpec

Infrastructure: Docker • Kubernetes

Database: postgresql • Mysql • Sqlite • Realm • MongoDB • Redis • Elastic Search

Project Management: JIRA • Redmine • Trello **Version Control:** Git • Perforce • Subversion

Real-time Services: Pusher • PubNub

Miscelleneous: GraphQL • Protobuf • RabbitMQ • Kafka • Apache JackRabbit • Big Data (Apache Hadoop, MapReduce, Sqoop, Hive, HBase) • Machine Learning (Scikit-learn, NumPy, Pandas) • Deep Learning (Keras)

Technical Articles

My technical articles, specially on Elixir/Phoenix and Machine Learning can be viewed and read at https://medium.com/@merajulislam

Past Professional Projects

Earthcar Taxi App (iOS, Android)

2017

Uber like Taxi app for Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Japan. Three different applications - User App (Android, Smartphone), User App (iOS, Smartphone) and Driver App (Android, Tab) along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile apps.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided engineers to implement features.
- Derived project estimation from client requirements, broke down features into sprints, worked with QA Engineers to define test specifications.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Collaborated with backend engineers for smooth integration of APIs/services with mobile apps.

Askul E-commerce App (iOS, Android)

2017

E-commerce applications developed for Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) Japan. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Backend APIs/services developed using Java (Spring Boot) by 3rd party in Japan.
- Conducted regular meeting and status reporting with Japan side project stakeholders.

A2MILKBAR App (iOS, Android)

2016

Departmental store management app developed for Australian client. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android platform along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Supervised backend APIs/services development using PHP and Node.js.

Samsung Gear S and Samsung Gear Fit Apps (iOS)

2015-2016

Developed commercial versions of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Apps to work with Tizen powered Gear S2 and Gear Fit 2.

- Developed in collaboration with Samsung HQ (South Korea).
- Conducted R&D, designed and developed Basic Accessory Protocol (BAP) on top of Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE). The protocol supports file transfer with pause/resume/cancel, CRC and re-transmission, QoS
- Designed and developed Webproxy module to support multiple Gear apps, such as Weather, S-Voice, Voice Memo, etc.
- Notifications using Apple Notification Center Service, along with notification settings, block notifications.
- Samsung Gear S https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-s/id1117310635?mt=8
- Samsung Gear Fit https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-fit/id1117312500?mt=8

Open Source Contribution

Linaro Project - http://www.linaro.org

2015

Led team of 3 engineers for making contribution to Open Source project (Linaro) - open source software for ARM SoCs and made decent contribution to their power management tools - powertop, powerdebug, idlestat, and pm-qa.

Xinu Project - https://github.com/xinu-os/xinu

2006-2007

Made significant contribution to MIPS port of Xinu kernel - exception and interrupt handler, timer, ethernet driver, etc.

Achievement/Awards

- 2017 Ranked 2nd in Monstar Lab ISUCON Tech Olympics (Web App Performance Tuning contest)
- 2017 Promoted as CTO of Mobile Technology Division
- 2015 Won Employee of the Year Award (SRBD)
- 2015 Won Iconic Team award for iOS Gear Manager Team for 2H of Y2015 (SRBD)

2014	Nominated as Employee of the Year (SRBD)
2014	Iconic Team award for Android Development Team for 2H of Y2014 (SRBD)
2013	Achieved Double promotion (promoted from Lead Engineer to Chief Engineer, SRBD)
2006-2007	Won Graduate Assistantship (Marquette University)
1999-2003	Won Dean's List Award (BUET)
1999-2003	Won University Merit Scholarship (BUET)
1996-2003	Won Board Merit Scholarship (Bangladesh Government)